Guide to the E. F. Craven Company Records, 1793-1991 and undated, bulk 1907-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files Series, 1852-1987, (1 container) (Box 58)
  Consists of papers related to organizations or topics of interest to members of the Craven family. Groupings include Better Schools and Roads, Inc.; Genealogy; Greensboro Y.M.C.A.; Juvenilia; and the Religious Society of Friends. Arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically by year within each subject.
  - Better Schools and Roads, 1949-1971 (Box 59)
  - Genealogy, 1852-1987, (5 folders) (Box 59)
  - Juvenilia, 1893, Sept. 26-1975, May 5, (2 folders) (Box 59)
  - Religious Society of Friends, 1891-1976 (Box 59)
  - Y.M.C.A., 1928-1933 (Box 59)
- Memorabilia Series, 1920-1948 and undated, (1 container) (Box 59)
  Promotional items such as pencils, rulers, and luggage tags distributed by E. F. Craven Company and suppliers.
  - Various memorabilia (Box 60)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1879-1978 and undated, (1 container) (Box 60)
  Includes a notebook of biblical texts for sermons, pages from datebooks and appointment calendars, mailing lists, and drafts of editorials. Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 61)
- Previously Restricted Materials, 1916-1987 and undated, bulk 1950s-1987, (8 boxes) (Box 61)
  Files contain various correspondence, business, legal, personal, and financial papers that had been restricted by F. Duval Craven for his lifetime. Material is now open to use. Materials relate to and were collected by F. Duval Craven, but many family members are represented, especially in the correspondence. The correspondence spans five decades and is divided into two groups: personal letters exchanged between F. Duval Craven and many family members, and business correspondence, much of it having to do with the Craven Company's contracts with the State of NC Highway Commission. Most of the correspondence is incoming, addressed to F. Duval Craven. Legal and financial papers include wills, legal contracts, legal suits and other disputes or issues, and memos and correspondence about the family business. The personal papers, a small group, include newspaper clippings, a few photographs, some memorabilia, post cards, grade school report cards, receipts from business/vacation trips, and campaign and political papers (electoral ballots)
  The final group of folders contain aptitude tests carried out by a national testing firm on Craven Company employees during the fifties and sixties. These folders offer a detailed record of testing methods in the corporate world of the fifties and sixties. Some of the test reports are annotated by Craven after many years as to the outcome of the employee's performance, and note his assessment of this type of psychological and character testing.
  The materials were sealed in envelopes. During processing they were kept in original order as found in envelopes (each folder or group of folders represents the contents of an envelope), then arranged by series in rough chronological order, with resulting date overlap between folders. Aptitude test folders are closed to research until 2016.
  - Correspondence Series, 1933-1986 (Box 61)
    - 1933-1978, (20 folders) (Box 62)
    - 1952-1981, (33 folders) (Box 63)
    - 1972-1986, (21 folders) (Box 64)
  - Legal and Financial Papers Series, 1916-1985 (Box 64)
    - 1916-1965, (22 folders) (Box 65)
    - 1967-1985, (21 folders) (Box 66)
  - Personal Papers Series, 1922-1987 (Box 66)
    - 1922-1966, (21 folders) (Box 67)
    - 1966-1987, (19 folders) (Box 68)
  - Aptitude Testing, 1958-1966 [CLOSED TO RESEARCH UNTIL 2016.] (Box 68)
    - 1922-1966, (3 folders) (Box 69)
- Oversize Materials (Box 69)
  - Financial Records Series (Box 69)
    - Papers, 1907-1979 (Box 70)
  - Legal Papers Series (Box 70)
    - Record of Indenture, 1812 (Box 70)
  - Visual Materials Series (Box 70)
    - Machinery (Box 70)
      - Photographs, 1908-1911, n.d. (Box 70)
    - People (Box 70)
      - Photographs, 1926-1959, n.d. (Box 70)
    - Places (Box 70)
      - Photographs, ca. 1920-1929, n.d. (Box 70)
  - Printed Materials Series (Box 70)
    - Machinery advertisements, n.d. (Box 70)
    - Machinery blueprints, 1908-1915 (Box 70)
    - E. F. Craven Co. Calendar, 1931 (Box 70)
    - Blueprints for E. F. Craven equipment shop, 1979 (Box 70)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 71)